<section id="example-fixed">
<title>Fixed-point Newton division</title>

<section>
<title>The algorithm and its verification</title>

<para>Let us suppose we want to invert a floating-point number on a
processor without a floating-point unit. The 24-bit mantissa has to be inverted
from a value between 0.5 and 1 to a value between 1 and 2. For the sake of this
example, the transformation is performed by Newton's iteration with fixed-point
arithmetic.</para>

<para>The mantissa is noted <code>d</code> and its exact reciprocal is
<code>R</code>. Newton's iteration is started with a first approximation
<code>r0</code> taken from a table containing reciprocals at precision
<texinline>\pm 2^{-8}</texinline>. Two iterations are then performed. The result
<code>r1</code> of the first iteration is computed on 16-bit words in order to
speed up computations. The result <code>r2</code> of the second iteration is
computed on full 32-bit words. We want to prove that this second result is close
enough to the infinitely precise reciprocal <code>R = 1/d</code>.</para>

<para>First, we define <code>R</code> as the reciprocal, and
<code>d</code> and <code>r0</code> as two fixed-point numbers that are
integer multiples of <texinline>2^{-24}</texinline> and
<texinline>2^{-8}</texinline> respectively. Moreover, <code>r0</code> is
an approximation of <code>R</code> and <code>d</code> is between 0.5 and
1.</para>

<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[R = 1 / d;

{ @FIX(d,-24) /\ d in [0.5,1] /\
  @FIX(r0,-8) /\ r0 - R in [-1b-8,1b-8] ->
  ... }]]></programlisting>

<para>Next we have the two iterations. Gappa's representation of
fixed-point arithmetic is high-level: the tool is only interested in the
weight of the least significant bit. The shifts that occur in an
implementation only have an impact on the internal representation of the
values, not on the values themselves.</para>

<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[r1 fixed<-14,dn>= r0 * (2 - fixed<-16,dn>(d) * r0);
r2 fixed<-30,dn>= r1 * (2 - d * r1);]]></programlisting>

<para>The property we are looking for is a bound on the absolute error
between <code>r2</code> and <code>R</code>.</para>

<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[{ ... -> r2 - R in ? }]]></programlisting>

<para>We expect Gappa to prove that <code>r2</code> is <texinline>R \pm
2^{-24}</texinline>. Unfortunately, this is not the case.</para>

<screen>Results for d in [0.5, 1] and @FIX(d, -24) and @FIX(r0, -8) and r0 - R in [-0.00390625, 0.00390625]:
r2 - R in [-1320985b-18 {-5.03916, -2^(2.33318)}, 42305669b-23 {5.04323, 2^(2.33435)}]</screen>

</section>

<section>
<title>Adding hints</title>

<para>With the previous script, Gappa computes a range so wide for <code>r2 -
R</code> that it is useless. This is not surprising: The tool does not know what
Newton's iteration is. In particular, Gappa cannot guess that such an iteration
has a quadratic convergence. Testing for <code>r1 - R</code> instead does not
give results any better.</para>

<para>Gappa does not find any useful relation between <code>r1</code> and
<code>R</code>, as the first one is a rounded multiplication while the second one is
an exact division. So we have to split the absolute error into two terms: a
rounding error we expect Gappa to compute, and the convergence due to Newton's
iteration.</para>

<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[{ ... ->
  r1 - r0 * (2 - d * r0) in ? /\ r0 * (2 - d * r0) - R in ? }]]></programlisting>

<para>Gappa now gives the answer below. Notice that the range of the rounding
error almost matches the precision of the computations.</para>

<screen>Results for d in [0.5, 1] and @FIX(d, -24) and @FIX(r0, -8) and r0 - R in [-0.00390625, 0.00390625]:
r0 * (2 - d * r0) - R in [-131585b-16 {-2.00783, -2^(1.00564)}, 263425b-17 {2.00977, 2^(1.00703)}]
r1 - r0 * (2 - d * r0) in [-255b-22 {-6.07967e-05, -2^(-14.0056)}, 201456639b-40 {0.000183224, 2^(-12.4141)}]</screen>

<para>So Gappa was fine with the rounding error, but not with the algorithmic
error. We can help Gappa by directly providing an expression of this error. So
we add a rule describing the quadratic convergence of Newton's iteration. And
since we also have to split <code>r1 - R</code>, we perform both operations in
one single rewriting
rule.</para>

<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[r1 - R -> (r1 - r0 * (2 - d * r0)) - (r0 - R) * (r0 - R) * d;]]></programlisting>

<para>A similar rule is then used for <code>r2 - R</code>.</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Full listing 1</title>

<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[R = 1 / d;

r1 fixed<-14,dn>= r0 * (2 - fixed<-16,dn>(d) * r0);
r2 fixed<-30,dn>= r1 * (2 - d * r1);

{ @FIX(d,-24) /\ d in [0.5,1] /\
  @FIX(r0,-8) /\ r0 - R in [-1b-8,1b-8] ->
  r2 - R in ? }

r1 - R -> (r1 - r0 * (2 - d * r0)) - (r0 - R) * (r0 - R) * d;
r2 - R -> (r2 - r1 * (2 - d * r1)) - (r1 - R) * (r1 - R) * d;]]></programlisting>

<para>Gappa answers that <texinline>r_2 = R \pm 2^{-24.7}</texinline>.</para>

<screen>Warning: although present in a quotient, the expression (d) may have not been tested for non-zeroness.

Results for d in [0.5, 1] and @FIX(d, -24) and @FIX(r0, -8) and r0 - R in [-0.00390625, 0.00390625]:
r2 - R in [-41710608584542209b-80 {-3.45022e-08, -2^(-24.7887)}, 8356605b-52 {1.85554e-09, 2^(-29.0055)}]</screen>

</section>

<section>
<title>Improving the rewriting rules</title>

<para>First of all, there is this warning message about <code>d</code> possibly
being zero. Indeed, <code>R</code> is the reciprocal of <code>d</code> and we
are using the fact that <code>R * d = 1</code>. So the rewriting rules cannot
be proved on their own. (But they can be proved in the context of the
problem, so there is no correctness issue.) In order to avoid this
warning, we can give the precise hypotheses such that the left hand sides
of the rewriting rules are equal to their right hand side without any
other assumption. This is indicated at the end of the rule.</para>

<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[r1 - R -> (r1 - r0 * (2 - d * r0)) - (r0 - R) * (r0 - R) * d   {d <> 0};]]></programlisting>

<para>Second, the rewriting rules are too specialized. For example, in the first
one, the occurrences of <code>r1</code> could be replaced by any other real
number and the rule would still be valid. Let us consider the problem again. We
wanted to split <code>r1 - R</code> into a rounding error and an algorithmic
error. So we could just say that <code>r1</code> is an approximation of
<code>r0 * (2 - d * r0)</code>.</para>

<programlisting language="gappa">r1 ~ r0 * (2 - d * r0);</programlisting>

<para>We are left with hinting Gappa at the quadratic convergence of Newton's
iterations.</para>

<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[r0 * (2 - d * r0) - R -> (r0 - R) * (r0 - R) * -d   { d <> 0};]]></programlisting>

<para>When generating a script for an external proof checker, Gappa will add
this rewriting rule as a global hypothesis. For example, when selecting the Coq
back-end with the option <code>-Bcoq</code>, the output contains the line
below.</para>

<programlisting language="coq"><![CDATA[Hypothesis a1 : (_d <> 0)%R -> r9 = r2.]]></programlisting>

<para>In this hypothesis, <code>_d</code> is the <code>d</code> variable of the
example, while <code>r9</code> and <code>r2</code> are short notations for
<code>r0 * (2 - d * r0) - R</code> and <code>(r0 - R) * (r0 - R) * -d</code>
respectively. In order to access the generated proof, the user has to prove
this hypothesis, which can be trivially done with Coq's <code>field</code>
tactic.</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Full listing 2</title>

<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[R = 1 / d;

r1 fixed<-14,dn>= r0 * (2 - fixed<-16,dn>(d) * r0);
r2 fixed<-30,dn>= r1 * (2 - d * r1);

{ @FIX(d,-24) /\ d in [0.5,1] /\
  @FIX(r0,-8) /\ r0 - R in [-1b-8,1b-8] ->
  r2 - R in ? }

r1 ~ r0 * (2 - d * r0);
r0 * (2 - d * r0) - R -> (r0 - R) * (r0 - R) * -d   { d <> 0 };
r2 ~ r1 * (2 - d * r1);
r1 * (2 - d * r1) - R -> (r1 - R) * (r1 - R) * -d   { d <> 0 };]]></programlisting>

<para>The answer is the same.</para>

<screen>Results for d in [0.5, 1] and @FIX(d, -24) and @FIX(r0, -8) and r0 - R in [-0.00390625, 0.00390625]:
r2 - R in [-41710608584542209b-80 {-3.45022e-08, -2^(-24.7887)}, 8356605b-52 {1.85554e-09, 2^(-29.0055)}]</screen>

<para>Another example of a Newton iteration is given in <xref linkend="why"/>.</para>

</section>
</section>
