<section id="example-x1mx">
<title>A simple example to start from: x * (1 - x)</title>

<section>
<title>The C program</title>

<para>Let us analyze the following function.</para>

<programlisting language="c"><![CDATA[float f(float x)
{
  assert(0 <= x && x <= 1);
  return x * (1 - x);
}]]></programlisting>

<para>This function computes the value <code>x * (1 - x)</code> for an argument
<code>x</code> between 0 and 1. The <type>float</type> type is meant to force
the compiler to use IEEE-754 single precision floating-point numbers. We also
assume that the default rounding mode is used: rounding to nearest number,
break to even on tie.</para>

<para>The function returns the value <texinline>x \otimes (1 \ominus x)</texinline>
instead of the ideal value <texinline>x \cdot (1 - x)</texinline> due to the
limited precision of the computations. If we rule out the overflow possibility
(floating-point numbers are limited, not only in precision, but also in range),
the returned value is also <texinline>\circ(x \cdot \circ(1 - x))</texinline>.
This o function is a unary operator related to the floating-point format and
the rounding mode used for the computations. This is the form Gappa works on.</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>First Gappa version</title>

<para>We first try to bound the result of the function. Knowing that
<code>x</code> is in the interval <code>[0,1]</code>, what is the enclosing
interval of the function result? It can be expressed as an implication: If
<code>x</code> is in <code>[0,1]</code>, then the
result is in ... something. Since we do not want to enforce some specific
bounds yet, we use a question mark instead of some explicit bounds.</para>

<para>The logical formula Gappa has to verify is enclosed between braces. The
rounding operator is a unary function <code>float&lt; ieee_32, ne &gt;</code>.
The result of this function is a real number that would fit in a IEEE-754 single
precision (<code>ieee_32</code>) floating-point number (<code>float</code>), if
there was no overflow. This number is potentially a subnormal number and it
was obtained by rounding the argument of the rounding operator toward nearest
even (<code>ne</code>).</para>

<para>The following Gappa script finds an interval such that the logical formula
describing our previous function is true.</para>

<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[{ x in [0,1] -> float<ieee_32,ne>(x * float<ieee_32,ne>(1 - x)) in ? }]]></programlisting>

<para>Gappa answers that the result is between 0 and 1. Without any help from
the user, they are the best bounds Gappa is able to prove.</para>

<screen>Results for x in [0, 1]:
[rounding_float,ne,24,149](x * [rounding_float,ne,24,149](1 - x)) in [0, 1]</screen>

</section>

<section>
<title>Defining notations</title>

<para>Directly writing the completely expanded logical formula is fine for small
formulas, but it may become tedious once the problem gets big enough. For this
reason, notations can be defined to avoid repeating the same terms over and over.
These notations are all written before the logical formula.</para>

<para>For example, if we want not only the resulting range of the function, but
also the absolute error, we need to write the expression twice. So we give it
the name <code>y</code>.</para>

<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[y = float<ieee_32,ne>(x * float<ieee_32,ne>(1 - x));
{ x in [0,1] -> y in ? /\ y - x * (1 - x) in ? }]]></programlisting>

<para>We can simplify the input a bit further by giving a name to the rounding
operator too.</para>

<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[@rnd = float<ieee_32, ne>;
y = rnd(x * rnd(1 - x));
{ x in [0,1] -> y in ? /\ y - x * (1 - x) in ? }]]></programlisting>

<para>These explicit rounding operators right in the middle of the expressions
make it difficult to directly express the initial C code. So we factor the
operators by putting them before the equal sign.</para>

<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[@rnd = float<ieee_32, ne>;
y rnd= x * (1 - x);
{ x in [0,1] -> y in ? /\ y - x * (1 - x) in ? }]]></programlisting>

<para>Please note that this implicit rounding operator only applies to the
results of arithmetic operations. In particular, <code>a rnd= b</code> is not
equivalent to <code>a = rnd(b)</code>. It is equivalent to <code>a = b</code>.</para>

<para>Finally, we can also give a name to the infinitely precise result of the
function to clearly show that both expressions have a similar arithmetic
structure.</para>

<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[@rnd = float< ieee_32, ne >;
y rnd= x * (1 - x);
z = x * (1 - x);

{ x in [0,1] -> y in ? /\ y - z in ? }]]></programlisting>

<para>On the script above, Gappa displays:</para>

<screen><![CDATA[Results for x in [0, 1]:
y in [0, 1]
y - z in [-1b-24 {-5.96046e-08, -2^(-24)}, 1b-24 {5.96046e-08, 2^(-24)}]]]></screen>

<para>Gappa displays the bounds it has computed. Numbers enclosed in braces are
approximations of the numbers on their left. These exact left numbers are
written in decimal with a power-of-two exponent. The precise format will be
described below.</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Complete version</title>

<para>Previously found bounds are not as tight as they could actually be. Let us
see how to expand Gappa's search space in order for it to find better bounds.
Not only Gappa will be able provide a proof of the optimal bounds for the result
of the function, but it will also prove a tight interval on the computational
absolute error.</para>

<section>
<title>Notations</title>

<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[x = rnd(xx);                           # x is a floating-point number
y rnd= x * (1 - x);                    # equivalent to y = rnd(x * rnd(1 - x))
z = x * (1 - x);]]></programlisting>

<para>The syntax for notations is simple. The left-hand-side identifier
is a name representing the expression on the right-hand side. Using one
side or the other in the logical formula is strictly equivalent. Gappa
will use the defined identifier when displaying the results and
generating the proofs though, in order to improve their
readability.</para>

<para>The second and third notations have already been presented. The first
one defines <code>x</code> as the rounded value of a real number <code>xx</code>.
In the previous example, we had not expressed this property of <code>x</code>:
it is a floating-point number. This additional piece of information will help
Gappa to improve the bound on the error bound. Without it, a theorem like
Sterbenz' lemma cannot apply to the <code>1 - x</code> subtraction.</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Logical formulas and numbers</title>

<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[{ x in [0,1] -> y in [0,0.25] /\ y - z in [-3b-27,3b-27] }]]></programlisting>

<para>Numbers and bounds can be written either in the usual scientific decimal
notation or by using a power-of-two exponent: <code>3b-27</code> means
<texinline>3 \cdot 2^{-27}</texinline>. Numbers can also be written with the
C99 hexadecimal notation: <code>0x0.Cp-25</code> is another way to express the
bound on the absolute error.</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Hints</title>

<para>Although we have given additional data through the type of <code>x</code>,
Gappa is not yet able to prove the formula. It needs some user hints.</para>

<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[z -> 0.25 - (x - 0.5) * (x - 0.5);     # x * (1 - x) == 1/4 - (x - 1/2)^2
y $ x;                                 # bound y by splitting the interval on x
y - z $ x;                             # bound y - z by splitting ...]]></programlisting>

<para>The first hint indicates to Gappa that both hand sides are equivalent:
When it tries to bound the left hand side, it can use the bounds it has found
for the right hand side. Please note that this rewriting only applies when Gappa
tries to bound the expression, not when it tries to bound a bigger
expression.</para>

<para>The two other hints indicate that Gappa should bound the
left-hand-side values by doing a <link linkend="hint-dichotomy">case
split</link> on the right-hand side. It only works if the logical
proposition requires explicit bounds for the expression on the left hand
side.</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Full listing</title>

<para>As a conclusion, here is the full listing of this example.</para>

<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[# some notations
@rnd = float<ieee_32, ne>;
x = rnd(xx);                           # x is a floating-point number
y rnd= x * (1 - x);                    # equivalent to y = rnd(x * rnd(1 - x))
z = x * (1 - x);                       # the value we want to approximate

# the logical property
{ x in [0,1] -> y in [0,0.25] /\ y - z in [-3b-27,3b-27] }

# hints
z -> 0.25 - (x - 0.5) * (x - 0.5);     # x * (1 - x) == 1/4 - (x - 1/2)^2
y $ x;                                 # bound y by splitting the interval on x
y - z $ x;                             # bound y - z by splitting ...]]></programlisting>

<para>Gappa gives the results below.</para>

<screen>Warning: z and 25e-2 - (x - 5e-1) * (x - 5e-1) are not trivially equal.
         Difference: (5e-1)^2 - (25e-2) - 2 * (x) * (5e-1) + (x)

Results for x in [0, 1]:
y in [0, 1b-2 {0.25, 2^(-2)}]
y - z in [-3b-27 {-2.23517e-08, -2^(-25.415)}, 3b-27 {2.23517e-08, 2^(-25.415)}]</screen>

<para>Note that Gappa checks the rewriting rules in order to provide early
detection of mistyping. Since this check does not involve computations on
decimal numbers, Gappa warns about the user hint on <code>z</code>. This false
positive can be avoided by adding the special comment
<code>#@ -Wno-hint-difference</code> before the offending rule.</para>

</section>

</section>
</section>
