<section>
<title>Syntax error messages</title>

<section>
<title>Error: foobar at line 17 column 42.</title>
<para>The Bison front-end has detected a syntax error at the given location.
The error message is usually unusable, so let us hope the location is enough
for you to find what the problem is.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa">f(x) = x + 1;</programlisting>
<screen>Error: syntax error, unexpected '(', expecting FUNID or '=' at line 1 column 2</screen>
</section>

<section>
<title>Error: unrecognized option 'bar'.</title>
<para>Gappa was invoked with an unknown option.</para>
<para>Variant: unrecognized option 'bar' at line 42. This error is
displayed for options embedded in the script.</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Error: the symbol foo is redefined...</title>
<para>A symbol cannot be defined more than once, even if the right hand sides
of every definitions are equivalent.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa">a = 1;
a = 1;</programlisting>
<para>Nor can it be defined after being used as an unbound variable.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa">b = a * 2;
a = 1;</programlisting>
</section>

<section>
<title>Error: foo is not a rounding operator...</title>
<para>Only rounding operators (unary function close to the identity function)
can be prepended to the equal sign in a definition.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[x add_rel<25,-100>= 1;]]></programlisting>
<screen>Error: relative,add,25,-100 is not a rounding operator at line 1 column 20</screen>
</section>

<section>
<title>Error: invalid parameters for foo...</title>
<para>A function template has been instantiated with an incorrect number of
parameters or with parameters of the wrong type.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[x = float<ieee_32,0>(y);]]></programlisting>
<screen>Error: invalid parameters for float at line 1 column 20</screen>
</section>

<section>
<title>Error: incorrect number of arguments when calling foo...</title>
<para>There are either less or more expressions between parentheses than
expected by the function.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[x = int<zr>(y, z);]]></programlisting>
<screen>Error: incorrect number of arguments when calling rounding_fixed,zr,0 at line 1 column 17</screen>
</section>

</section>

<section>
<title>Error messages</title>

<section>
<title>Error: undefined intervals are restricted to conclusions.</title>
<para>You are not allowed to use an interrogation mark for an interval that
appears as an hypothesis in the logical formula.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[{ x in ? -> x + 1 in [0,1] }]]></programlisting>
<para>Notice that this condition is checked after the proposition has been
reduced to several elementary propositions. As a consequence, an interrogation
mark on the right hand side of an implication can still cause Gappa to fail.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[{ x + 1 in [0,1] \/ not (x in ?) }]]></programlisting>
</section>

<section>
<title>Error: the range of foo is an empty interval.</title>
<para>An interval has been interpreted as having reverted bounds.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[{ x in [2,1] }]]></programlisting>
<screen><![CDATA[Error: the range of x is an empty interval.]]></screen>
<para>Interval bounds are replaced by binary floating-point numbers. As a
consequence, Gappa can encounteer an empty interval when it tightens a range
appearing in a goal. For example, the empty set is the biggest representable
interval that is a subset of the singleton {1.3}. So Gappa fails to prove the
following property.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[{ 1.3 in [1.3,1.3] }]]></programlisting>
<screen><![CDATA[Error: the range of 13e-1 is an empty interval.]]></screen>
</section>

<section>
<title>Error: a zero appears as a denominator in a rewriting rule.</title>
<para>Gappa has a detected that a divisor is trivially equal to zero in an
expression that appears in a rewriting rule. This is most certainly an error.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[{ 1 in ? }
y -> y * (x - x) / (x - x);]]></programlisting>
</section>

</section>

<section id="warning-messages1">
<title>Warning messages</title>

<section>
<title>Warning: the hypotheses on foo are trivially contradictory, skipping.</title>
<para>If an expression is enclosed in several hypotheses, and if the
intersection of their ranges is empty, then the proposition is trivially true.
As a consequence, Gappa skips the proposition instead of proving it.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[{ x <= 2 /\ x >= 3 -> x in ? }]]></programlisting>
<screen>Warning: the hypotheses on x are trivially contradictory, skipping.</screen>
</section>

<section>
<title>Warning: foo is being renamed to bar.</title>
<para>When a definition <code>toto = expr</code> is given to Gappa, the name
<code>toto</code> is associated to the expression <code>expr</code>. This name
is then used whenever Gappa needs to output <code>expr</code>. If another
definition <code>titi = expr</code> is later provided, the new name supersedes
the name given previously.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa">a = 42;
b = 42;
{ a - b in ? }</programlisting>
<screen>Warning: a is being renamed to b at line 2 column 7

Results:
b - b in [0, 0]</screen>
</section>

<section>
<title>Warning: although present in a quotient, the expression foo may not
have been tested for non-zeroness.</title>
<para>When Gappa verifies that both sides of a user rewriting rule are
equivalent, it does not generate additional constraints to verify that
denominators appearing in the expressions are not zero. For example, the rule
<code>1 / (1 / x) -&gt; x</code> only applies when <code>x</code> is not zero;
yet Gappa does not test for it.</para>
<para>No warning messages are displayed when constraints are added to the
rewriting rule (whether these constraints are sufficient or not).
E.g. <code>1 / (1/ x) -&gt; x { x &lt;&gt; 0 }</code>.</para>
<para>Option switch: <code>-W[no-]null-denominator</code>.</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Warning: foo and bar are not trivially equal.</title>
<para>When Gappa verifies the rule <code>toto -&gt; titi</code>, it first
performs the subtraction of both sides. Then it normalizes this expression in
the field of polynomial fractions with integer coefficients. If this result is
not zero, Gappa warns about it.</para>
<para>As the normalization only deals with polynomials and integers, false
positive may appear when the expressions involve numerical values or square
roots or absolute values.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[{ 1 in ? }
x * (y - 2) -> x * y - x;  # not equal
1b-2 -> 0.2 + 0.05;        # equal, but needs numerical computations
sqrt(x * x) -> |x|;        # equal, but involves square root and absolute value]]>
</programlisting>
<screen>Warning: x * (y - 2) and x * y - x are not trivially equal.
         Difference: -(x)
Warning: 1b-2 and 2e-1 + 5e-2 are not trivially equal.
         Difference: -(2e-1) - (5e-2) + (1b-2)
Warning: sqrt(x * x) and |x| are not trivially equal.
         Difference: (sqrt(x * x)) - (|x|)</screen>
<para>Option switch: <code>-W[no-]hint-difference</code>.</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Warning: bar is a variable without definition, yet it is unbound.</title>
<para>Neither an expression is associated to the identifier <code>titi</code>
nor it is a sub-term of any of the bounded expressions of the logical property.
This may mean an identifier was in fact mistyped.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa">{ x - x in ? }</programlisting>
<screen>Warning: x is a variable without definition, yet it is unbound.</screen>
<para>Option switch: <code>-W[no-]unbound-variable</code>.</para>
</section>

</section>

<section id="warning-messages2">
<title>Warning messages during proof computation</title>

<section>
<title>Warning: no path was found for foo.</title>
<para>The expression <code>toto</code> appears in one of the goals, yet Gappa
does not have any theorem that could be used to compute this expression or one
of its sub-terms.</para>
</section>

<!--
<section>
<title>Warning: generated hypotheses were not proved, skipping.</title>
<para>Gappa has created additional hypotheses in order to prove a property.
These hypotheses could not be satisfied so the property is discarded, since it
contains more hypotheses than required. For example, in order to prove
<code>A /\ (B -&gt; C) -&gt; D</code>, Gappa creates two new properties:
<code>A -&gt; D \/ B</code> and <code>A /\ C -&gt; D</code>. If Gappa was
unable to prove the first property, there is no point in trying to prove the
second one, since it contains an additional hypothesis.</para>
</section>
-->

<section>
<title>Warning: hypotheses are in contradiction, any result is true.</title>
<para>Gappa has found a contradiction among the hypotheses. So, instead of
proving the goals, it will just prove <code>False</code>, since it implies any
possible goal.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[{ x in [1,2] /\ x - 1 in [3,4] -> x in [5,6] }]]></programlisting>
<screen>Results for x in [1, 2] and x - 1 in [3, 4]:
Warning: hypotheses are in contradiction, any result is true.</screen>
</section>

<section>
<title>Warning: no contradiction was found.</title>
<para>Gappa had no specific goal to prove, and as such was expecting to find a
contradiction and prove it. Yet none were found.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[{ x in [1,2] -> not x + 1 in [2,3] }]]></programlisting>
<screen>Results for x in [1, 2] and x + 1 in [2, 3]:
Warning: no contradiction was found.</screen>
</section>

<section>
<title>Warning: some enclosures were not satisfied.</title>
<para>Only part of a conjunction of goals was proved to be true. Gappa was
unable to prove some other expressions or formulas, which are displayed after
the message.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[{ x in [1,2] -> x + 1 in ? /\ x + 2 in [2,3] }]]></programlisting>
<screen>Results for x in [1, 2]:
x + 1 in [1b1 {2, 2^(1)}, 3]
Warning: some enclosures were not satisfied.
Missing x + 2</screen>
</section>

<section>
<title>Warning: when foo is in i1, bar is in i2 potentially outside of i3.</title>
<para>When Gappa applies a case splitting <code>titi $ toto</code>, it splits
the interval of <code>toto</code> until the goal containing <code>titi</code>
holds for any sub-interval. If the maximal dichotomy depth has been reached yet
the property still does not hold, the warning message displays the failing
sub-interval (the leftmost one) and the computed ranges.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[#@-Edichotomy=3
{ x in [1,2] -> x + 1 in [2,2.75] }
x + 1 $ x;]]></programlisting>
<screen>Results for x in [1, 2]:
Warning: when x is in [7b-2 {1.75, 2^(0.807355)}, 15b-3 {1.875, 2^(0.906891)}], x + 1 is in [11b-2 {2.75, 2^(1.45943)}, 23b-3 {2.875, 2^(1.52356)}] potentially outside of [1b1 {2, 2^(1)}, 11b-2 {2.75, 2^(1.45943)}].
Warning: some enclosures were not satisfied.
Missing x + 1</screen>
<para>Variant: when foo is in i1, bar is not computable. This warning is
displayed if no bounds on <code>titi</code> can even be computed.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[{ x in [-2,1] -> x / x in [1,1] }
x / x $ x;]]></programlisting>
<screen>Results for x in [-2, 1]:
Warning: when x is in [-1b-99 {-1.57772e-30, -2^(-99)}, 1b-100 {7.88861e-31, 2^(-100)}], x / x is not computable.
Warning: some enclosures were not satisfied.
Missing x / x</screen>
<para>Option switch: <code>-W[no-]dichotomy-failure</code>.</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Warning: case split on foo has not produced any interesting new result.</title>
<para>This warning is displayed when Gappa is successful in finding a case
split that satisfies the goals, yet the results obtained on the sub-intervals
are not interesting: they have already been proved through a simpler analysis.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[{ x in [1,2] -> x + 1 in ? }
$ x;]]></programlisting>
<screen>Results for x in [1, 2]:
Warning: case split on x has not produced any interesting new result.
x + 1 in [1b1 {2, 2^(1)}, 3]</screen>
<para>Option switch: <code>-W[no-]dichotomy-failure</code>.</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Warning: case split on foo has no range to split.</title>
<para>This warning is displayed when Gappa is unable to find the initial range
on which to split cases.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[{ x in [-1,1] -> 1 in ? }
$ 1 / x;]]></programlisting>
<screen>Results for x in [-1, 1]:
Warning: case split on 1 / x has no range to split.
1 in [1, 1]</screen>
<para>Option switch: <code>-W[no-]dichotomy-failure</code>.</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Warning: case split on foo is not goal-driven anymore.</title>
<para>This warning is displayed when Gappa is supposed to find the best case
split for proving a property, yet it does not know the range for this property
or it has already proved it.</para>
<programlisting language="gappa"><![CDATA[{ x in [-1,1] -> x + 1 in ? }
x + 1 $ x;]]></programlisting>
<screen>Results for x in [-1, 1]:
Warning: case split on x is not goal-driven anymore.
x + 1 in [0, 1b1 {2, 2^(1)}]</screen>
<para>Option switch: <code>-W[no-]dichotomy-failure</code>.</para>
</section>

</section>
